A while back, I released a breakdown of
a big study looking at something called
a vilpa, which is in basic terms an
extremely short bout of intense physical
activity, though not exercise, but
through day-to-day activities like, I
don't know, groceries or walking and
plenty of other examples. It can
literally last as little as just a few
minutes. In that breakdown, we discussed
how these bursts of physical activity
have a noticeable impact at reducing
all-c cause mortality as well as
cardiovascular disease. So, I got to
wondering how exactly that happens if
it's such a small amount of work. That's
where I stumbled across this study where
people engaged in really simple exercise
that simply stimulated the musculature
for a few minutes at a time.
Technically, they did this 20 times
over, but I'm not as interested in the
exercise done 20 times. I'm more
interested in the first exposure lasting
only a few minutes like a Vilpa. The
researchers ended up measuring something
called shear stress which is the
friction to an area in this case the
blood vessel. Think of it like a sliding
force rubbing against the blood vessel
wall. So what would that force be in the
context of cardiovascular health? Well,
your blood. It has viscosity. So it's
thick and that blood rubs against the
internal pipe work of your blood vessels
throughout the body. But if you've been
following physionic for a moment or two,
you already know that your blood vessels
aren't just well pipe work. Uh they're a
mesh of live cells with an initial
lining of cells called endothelial cells
facing the bloodstream. Anyway, this
shear stress is applied to those cells.
So you can imagine that has some
biologically relevant effect. Looking at
the data, the dark dots are the
physically active condition and the
white dots are the non-physically active
individuals. If the dot goes up, that
means there's more shear stress applied
to the walls of the artery. Obviously,
in every exercise condition, there's a
huge increase in shear stress. But like
I said, what is most interesting is the
initial exposure. So, the first few
minutes because there's already a huge
increase. Now, that doesn't sound too
pleasant. A bunch of sheer stress, four
to fivefold force being applied to the
blood vessel wall, those poor cells. But
your body ain't no wimp, and neither are
those microscopic cells that make up
your blood vessels. When the researchers
measured what happens to those cells,
they show why your cardiovascular health
improves from this spike in sheer stress
as opposed to beating them black and
blue. The reality is, while endothelial
cells, that first lining of cells, are
small, they are mighty and crafty. when
they get punched by the force of the
blood ramming into them, they deform.
And that deformation is one way they can
sense to change their behavior. So to
summarize real quick, short bursts of
physical activity spike the force
applied to the blood vessel cells like
endothelial cells and changes their
behavior. Okay, but exactly how and why
is this not a problem? Inside your
endothelial cells is an enzyme called
enos. Enos is responsible for producing
a potent molecule called nitric oxide.
That nitric oxide when released from the
endothelial cells interacts with the
muscle cells in charge of squeezing or
relaxing the blood vessel and convinces
the muscle cells to relax the blood
vessel. In so doing, blood pressure and
likely shear stress is reduced. If we
look at the data, if the bars go up,
that means there's more of this ENOS
enzyme present. And on top of that, it's
been activated. And clearly we only see
this increase in the physically active
condition after the physical activity.
If you prefer the visual image of a
single cell, the top has enos fluoresing
in red. Clearly there's more enos inside
the cell post physical activity. So this
would mean that there's a high
probability that the cell is producing
more nitric oxide thereby opening the
blood vessel in response to the sheer
stress coming from the physical activity
and showing a greater ability to be
dynamic. This all means this is one
mechanism by which short bursts of
physical activity could have an impact.
Now to be fair there are some
assumptions here since the type of
exercise is different and the
endothelial cell measurements of enos
are after multiple bouts. Still clearly
something is working and this is a quick
mechanism that does fit. Still, that
raises this question of, well, if sheer
stress is so high after a short bout of
physical activity and we see a
beneficial molecule produced, why
wouldn't something like high blood
pressure, which might raise sheer stress
consistently, also have a protective
effect? Well, I'll bet you might be able
to come up with the answer for yourself.
But in the meantime, if you're
interested in access to my complete
analysis on Vilpa, which is vigorous
intermittent lifestyle physical activity
and how to use short bursts of regular
daily activity, so not exercise, to your
advantage in reducing mortality risk,
check out the Physionic Insiders. My
complete breakdown is there. Oh, and you
also get access to my private podcasts,
live sessions with me, weekly articles
with actionable steps, protocols, and
guides, and even more. Anyway, the point
being it's an educational wonderland
full of fairies. The link to join is in
the description box. Hope to see you
there. Now, in the meantime, let's get
back to the problem at hand. So, there
are multiple reasons for why physical
activity shear stress is good and high
blood pressure stress is bad. For one, I
left out the word shear in the last
sentence because high blood pressure
doesn't always produce shear stress. It
produces consistent vessel wall strain
that is perpendicular to the vessel, not
necessarily shear stress running along
the wall. But assuming it did, there is
a need to allow the cells to return to
their original state. Constantly
flattening the cells and expecting them
to respond by widening the blood vessel
is maladaptive. Physical activity sheer
stress is temporary and of course leads
to other positive changes. So, a simple
study and certainly not all-encompassing
in relation to why just a few minutes of
not even exercise but physical activity
can reduce our cardiovascular disease
risk and by extension our mortality
risk. Even short bouts can encourage
increased levels of a potent enzyme
called enos which associates with
increased sheer stress and applied to
the blood vessel wall cells. If you're
interested in how to take advantage of
all this for yourself, I'll link my
video on a vilpas right here. So,
vigorous intermittent lifestyle physical
activity for you.